Syed Sohail Hashmi

Pakistan: House 319, Street 73, G-11/2, Islamabad, Pakistan | Office Phone +92-51-2510396, Cell Phone +92-301-8509080 Email: syed sohail hashmi@yahoo.com; sohailhashmi76@gmail.com Skype: Syed.Sohail.Hashmi

Summary

An Associate of Certified Public Accountant (ACPA) and have done MBA with majors in finance. Have worked in multicultural/International environments (South Asia and Central Asia) and have the ability to handle multiple tasks and work under pressure in a fast paced and complex environment. Ten years of hands on experience in financial management, accounting, grant management/ reporting, internal audit, risk assessment, organizational set up, automation of organizations, designing of financial, administration & operational policies and procedures. Have conducted capacity building workshops for finance and non finance staff for various organizations. Specialist of different accounting software's (SUN Financials, QB, and Peachtree etc) and Microsoft Office at professional level.

Areas of Expertise and professional strengths include:

- Financial Planning, Budgeting and Forecasting
- Internal & External Financial Reporting
- Grant Management
- Capacity Building and trainings

- Financial and Cost Analysis
- Financial monitoring and evaluations
- Budget monitoring and reporting Cash Management and Banking
- System Analysis and designing
 - Internal Auditing & Risk Assessment
- Partners assessments

Familiar with Non Profit Organization's Donors financial management and reporting mechanism:

AusAid & Aus Care, Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA), Care International, DFID (UK Department for International Development), Disaster Emergency Committee of UK (DEC), International Federation for Red Cross & Red Crescent Societies (IFRCS), The Humanitarian Aid department of the European Commission (ECHO) and United States Agency for International Development (USAID).

Professional Experience

Managing Director-Management Consultant (Self Employed) July 2011 to date

Management consultant focusing on strategic, unbiased and objective advisory services which assist organizations in improving productivity and overall performance. Advisory expertise covers areas such as financial performance, planning and development, assessments, resource acquisition, financial management, grant management, staff management, internal audit & risk management, monitoring & evaluations and training & development.

Regional Finance Manager -Pakistan and Central Asia Region -American Red Cross August 2006- to June 2011 **Key Responsibilities**

Developed financial management, administration, and procurement policies, procedures and reporting systems in the light of Am Cross international policies framework for ARC operations in Pakistan and Central Asia. Played a vital role while being a part of the senior management team during the process of Am Cross strategic planning and start up and implementation of the operations in Pakistan and Central Asia.

Supported fund raising function of Am Cross while submitting proposal and communication with the donors. One of the successes was getting a key role in DIPECHI VI ("Building sustainable community resilience through Disaster Risk Reduction in Central Asia") a famous project of ECHO.

Ensured effective internal and external reporting to the stakeholders. Conducted partner's evaluations and internal audits. Conducted capacity building programs for finance and non finance staff of Am Cross and partner organizations in Pakistan and Central Asian countries.

Action Aid International August 2002- to August 2006

Finance Coordinator -Action Aid International-Pakistan and Sri Lanka (August 2002 to August 2006) **Key Responsibilities**

Designed financial management systems, grant management systems, procurement and administration policies and procedures for AAI Sri Lanka and Pakistan. For the first time, introduced accounting software for partner organizations of AAI. The software supported financial accounting, internal and external customized reporting, inventory controls, asset management, grant management etc

Coordinated several internal and external audits. Managed mutli donor projects in Pakistan and Sri Lanka and obtained clean audit reports. Designed internal and external reporting mechanisms with the help of customized financial software's for AAI head office and provincial and project offices in Pakistan and Sri Lanka.

Conducted capacity building trainings focusing on financial, administration, internal audit, and grant management systems for AAI (finance and non finance staff) and partner organizations in Pakistan and Sri Lanka.

Position held during working for AAI

- a) Finance Coordinator AAI Pakistan Head Office: August 2002-Jan 2005
- b) Finance Manager AAI Sri Lanka: Feb 2005 April 2005
- c) Finance Advisor AAI Sri Lanka: May 2005 Dec 2005
- d) Finance Coordinator AAI Pakistan: Jan 2006 August 2006

Financial Management Consultancy

<u>Finance Consultant - Fusion i Tech (Pvt) Ltd Co. (US-Software Development company) Mar-2003 To Dec-2004</u> Key Responsibilities

Designed and implemented financial and administration policies & procedures and reporting mechanisms.

Ensured effective financial management

Ensured the compliance of the local statutory laws and reporting to Income Tax and Securities Exchange Commission of Pakistan SECP

Project Analysis and report to directors

Coordinating with the external audit

Education

Qualifications	Institutions	Year
Associate of Certified Public	The Association of Certified Public	2012
Accountant (ACPA)-UK	Accountants, UK	
Associate of Certified Public	ICPAP	2012
Accountant (ACPA)-Pakistan		
MBA-Finance	Al-Khair University	2003
B.Com	Punjab College of Commerce	1996
FSc (Pre-engineering)	Sir Syed Science College	1994
Matric	Saint Mary's Academy Lalazar,	1992
	Rawalpindi	

Training Attended

- Grant Management Kiev, Ukraine (October, 2010)
- Budging for proposals and Donor Reporting Almaty, Kazakhstan (September, 2010)
- Securities and risk management in Emergencies Islamabad, Pakistan (May, 2010)
- Procurement, planning and execution Islamabad, Pakistan (March 2009)
- Assessing NGO Capacity: An Overview of Tools & Applications Islamabad, Pakistan (February 2007)
- USAID and American Red Cross Rules and Regulations, Islamabad, Pakistan (December 2006)
- Opening and closing field offices, Islamabad, Pakistan (September 2006)
- Sun financial software training for professionals, Bangkok (November 2005)
- Training of Trainers Colombo, Sri Lanka (September 2005))
- Financial Management in Emergencies for NGOs, Colombo (July, 2005)
- International Emergency workshop, Colombo (April, 2005)

• Financial Analyst workshop-Lahore, Pakistan (September, 2003)

Trainings Conducted

I have conducted several finance trainings for NGOs in Pakistan, Sri Lanka and Central Asian countries. The trainings contents were financial management of organization and for non finance manager, risk assessment, internal controls and financial reporting for internal and external stakeholders. These trainings were conducted while I was working with ActionAid International and American Red Cross from 2002 through 2011.

I have designed organizational polices and procedures and introduced automation of financial management system by conducting workshops and on job trainings.

Teaching

I have taught finance subjects in business schools and universities. The details are as follows:

Subjects	Institutions	Year
Financial Accounting-B.Com	Scholars college of commerce	2000-2001
Cost Accounting-BBA	Iqra Univesity	2006
Financial Accounting-BBA	Iqra Univesity	2006
Financial Accounting-MBA	MAJU	2006

Computer/Accounting Software's Skills:

Sun Financials
QuickBooks and Quicken
Peachtree
Ms Office

Customized accounting software's

Reference

Khayyam Mushir Cell#: +92-3365150006

Email: khayyam.mushir@pk.ey.com

Senior Manager Ernst & Young Ford Rhodes Sidat Hyder, Islamabad, Pakistan

Ata-UL-Haseeb

Cell# +92-333-5229874, Landline +92-51-8358874 Fax +92-51-8358875,

Email: haseeb.ata@enterprisedb.com; Head Senior Manager Finance and Administration

Adeel Anwar

Cell# +92-3224003706

Email: adeelanwar_pk@yahoo.com; Head of OD & TRG at Warid Telecom International Ltd, Lahore, Pakistan